<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Charles R. Charles by the grace of God, king of Scotland, England, France, and Ireland, defender of the faith. To our lovits [blank] maissars ... greeting. Whereas for the removing of the disorders ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1638-12-08</title>
            <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852117</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17424</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1362:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Charles R. Charles by the grace of God, king of Scotland, England, France, and Ireland, defender of the faith. To our lovits [blank] maissars ... greeting. Whereas for the removing of the disorders ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1638-12-08</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Young, printer to the Kings most excellent Majestie. Cum privilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Against acknowledging the Glasgow Assembly.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Given .. the eighth day of December .. 1638.</note>
                  <note>Title from opening words of text, A2r; imprint from A1r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17424:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17424:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprinted at Edinburgh by Robert Young, Printer to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M PRIVILEGIO.</hi> Anno 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17424:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17424:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>Charles R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES by the grace of God, king of Scotland, England, France, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, defender of the faith.</signed>
               <salute>To our Lovits Maiſſars, Her aulds, Purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, our Sheriffs, in that part conjunctly and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpecially conſtitute, greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas for the removing of the diſorders which had happened of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17424:3"/>late within this our kingdome, and for ſetling of a perfect peace in the church and common-wealth thereof, we were pleaſed to cauſe indict a free gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſembly to be holden at Glaſgow the xxi. of November laſt: And for our ſubjects their better content and aſſurance that they ſhould be freed of all ſuch things as by their petitions and ſupplications gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in to the Lords of our privie Councell, they ſeemed to be grieved at, We in ſome ſort preveened the aſſembly, by diſcharging by our proclamation the ſervice book, book of canons, and high commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, freed and liberate our ſubjects from the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the five articles, eximed all miniſters at their entrie from giving any other oath then that which is contained in the act of parliament, made all perſons both eccleſiaſticall and civill lyable to the cenſure of Parliament, generall Aſſembly, or any other ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatorie competent, according to the nature of their offence: had declared all by-gone diſorders ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely forgotten and forgiven: and laſt, for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to all poſteritie the truth and liberty of religion, did command the confeſſion of faith, and band for maintenance thereof, and of authoritie in defence of the ſame, ſubſcribed by our deare Father, and his houſhold, <hi>in anno</hi> 1580. to be renued and ſubſcribed again by our ſubjects here: And albeit that this our gracious and pious command, in ſtead of obedience and ſubmiſsion, rancountred open and publick oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and proteſtation againſt the ſame: And that they continued their daily and hourely guarding and watching our Caſtle of Edinburgh, ſuffering nothing to be imported therein, but at their diſcretion, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17424:3"/>and impeding any importation of ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or other neceſſaries whatſoever to any of our houſes within this kingdome: Denying to us their ſoveraigne Lord that libertie and freedome, which the meaneſt of them aſſume to themſelves (an act without precedent or example in the chriſtian world) Like as they ſpared not boldly and openly to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their conventions and councell tables of Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, Gentrie, Miniſters and Burgeſſes within the city of Edinburgh, where not regarding the lawes of the kingdome, without warrant of authoritie, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veened, aſſembled, and treated upon matters; as well eccleſiaſticall as civill, ſent their injunctions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections throughout the countrey to their ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate tables, and other under miniſters appointed by them for that effect. And under colour and pretext of religion, exercing an unwarranted libertie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired obedience to their unlawfull and illegall directions, to the ſeene prejudice of authoritie, and lawfull monarchicall government. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it was evidently manifeſt by the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall and unformall courſe taken in the election of the commiſſioners for the aſſembly, whereof ſome of them were under the cenſure of this church, ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cenſure of the church of Ireland, ſome long ſince baniſhed for open and avowed teaching againſt monarchie, others of them ſuſpended, and ſome admitted to the miniſterie contrary to the form preſcribed by the lawes of this kingdome, others of them rebels, and at the horne, ſome of them confined, and all of them by oath and ſubſcription bound to the overthrow of epiſcopall government. And by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17424:4"/>this and other their under-hand working, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate informations and perſwaſions, have given juſt ground of ſuſpicion of their partialitie, and ſo made themſelves unfit judges of what concerneth epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie. And als albeit it was ſufficiently cleared by the peremptorie and illegall procedures of the presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, who at their own hand by order of law, and without due forme of proceſſe, thruſt out mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators lawfully eſtabliſhed, and placed others, whom they found moſt inclinable to their turbulent humors, aſſociate to themſelves for chooſing of the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners to the aſſembly, a laick elder out of each pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, who being in moſt places equall, if not moe in number then the miniſterie, made choice both of the miniſters, who ſhould be commiſſioners from the presbyteries, as alſo of a laick elder, (which in time will prove to be of a dangerous conſequence, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a heavie burden to the libertie of church and church men) being more directed therein by the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of the foreſaid pretended tables, then by their own judgements, as appeared by the ſeverall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſent from them (far contrary to the lawes of this countrey, and lowable cuſtome of this church) ſome whereof were produced and exhibit by our Commiſſioner, and publickly read: One whereof, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect to the Noblemen and Barons of each presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, doth among many other odde paſſages, require diligence, leſt (ſay they) by our own ſilineſſe and treacherie we loſe ſo faire an occaſion of our liberty both chriſtian and civill; a ſtrange phraſe to proceed from dutifull or loyall hearted ſubjects. The other to the moderators of the ſeverall presbyteries, under
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17424:4"/>the title of PRIVATE INSTRUCTIONS, AUGUST 27. firſt, containeth that theſe private inſtructions ſhall be diſcovered to none, but to brethren well affected to the cauſe: ſecondly, order muſt be taken, that none be choſen ruling elders but covenanters, and theſe well affected to the buſineſſe: thirdly, that where the miniſter is not well affected, the ruling elder be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the commiſſioners of the ſhire, and ſpoken to particularly for that effect: fourthly, that they be carefull that no chappelmen, chaptermen, or a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter juſtice of peace, be choſen, although covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, except they have publickly renounced, or decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the unlawfulneſſe of their places: fifthly, that the ruling elders come from every church, in equall number with the miniſters; and if the miniſter op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to put themſelves in poſſeſſion, notwithſtanding of any oppoſition: ſixthly, that the commiſſioner of the ſhire cauſe conveen before him the ruling elder of every kirk choſen before the day of the election, and enjoyn them upon their oath, that they give vote to none but to thoſe who are named already at the meeting at Edinburgh: ſeventhly, that where there is a nobleman in the bounds of the presbytery, he be choſen, and where there is none, there be choſen a barron, or one of the beſt quality, and he only a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanter: eighthly, that the ableſt man in every preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery be provided to diſpute <hi>de poteſtate ſupremi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus in Eccleſiaſticis preſertim in convocandis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliis, &amp;c.</hi> Whereby it is moſt evident what prelimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, indirect and partiall courſes, and dangerous propoſitions have been uſed in the preparations and elections to this pretended aſſembly. By which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17424:5"/>unlawfull doings, although we had ſufficient reaſon to have diſcharged the meeting of the ſaid aſſembly, yet we were pleaſed patiently to attend the ſame, ſtill hoping that when they were met together by the preſence of our Commiſſioner, and aſſiſtance of ſome well affected ſubjects, who were to be there, and by their own ſeeing the reall performance of what was promiſed by our proclamation, they ſhould have been induced to return to the due obedience of ſubjects. But when we perceived that their turbulent diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did increaſe, as was manifeſt by their repairing to the ſaid pretended aſſembly with great troups and bands of men, all boddin in fear of war, with guns, and piſtolets, contrary to the laws of this kingdome, and in high contempt of our proclamation at Edinburgh the 16. day of November laſt: And alſo by the perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory refuſing to the aſſeſſors, authorized by us (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though fewer in number then our deareſt father was in uſe to have) the power of voting in this aſſembly, as formerly they had done in all others, openly aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that we, nor our Commiſſioner, had no further power there then the meaneſt commiſſioner of their number: and by their partiall and unjuſt refuſing, and not ſuffering to be read the reaſons and arguments gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in by the biſhops, and their adherents to our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, why they ought not to proceed to the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a moderator, neither yet to the trying and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the commiſſioners, before they were heard, though in our name they were earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired thereto by our Commiſſioner: and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that our Commiſſioner by warrant from us, gave in under his hand a ſufficient declaration of all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17424:5"/>that was contained in our late proclamation, bearing likewayes our pleaſure of the regiſtration of the ſame in the books of aſſembly, for ful aſſurance of the truth and purity of religion to all our good ſubjects, as doth clearly appear by the declaration it ſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the tenor follows. The kings Majeſty being infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that many of his good ſubjects have apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that by the introducing of the ſervice book, and book of canons, the inbringing of ſuperſtition hath been intended, hath been graciouſly pleaſed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, like as by theſe he doth diſcharge the ſervice book, and book of canons, and the practiſe of them, and either of them, and annulls and reſcinds all acts of councell, proclamations, and other acts and deeds whatſoever, that have been made or publiſhed for eſtabliſhing them, or either of them, and declares the ſame to be null, and to have no force nor effect in time coming. The kings Majeſtie, as he conceived, for the eaſe and benefit of the ſubject, eſtabliſhed the high commiſion, that thereby juſtice might be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and the faults and errours of ſuch perſons as are made lyable thereto, taken order with, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the more conveniencie, and leſſe trouble to the people. But finding his gracious intention there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be miſtaken, hath been pleaſed to diſcharge, like as by theſe he doth diſcharge the ſame, and all acts and deeds whatſoever made for eſtabliſhing thereof. And the kings Majeſtie being informed, that the urging of the five articles of Pearth aſſembly hath bred diſtraction in the church and eſtate, hath been graciouſly pleaſed to take the ſame into his royall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17424:6"/>conſideration, and for the quiet and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of this countrey hath not only diſpenſed with the practiſe of the ſaids articles, but alſo diſcharged all and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever perſons from urging the practiſe thereof, upon either laick or eccleſiaſticall perſon whatſoever, and hath freed all his ſubjects from all cenſure and pains, whether eccleſiaſticall or ſecular, for not urging, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing, or obeying them, or any of them, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any thing contained in the acts of parliament, or generall aſſembly in the contrary. And his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie is further contented, that the aſſembly take the ſame ſo far to their conſideration, as to repreſent it to the next parliament, there to be ratified as the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ſhall finde fitting. And becauſe it hath been pretended that oaths have been adminiſtrate different from that which is ſet down in the acts of parliament, his Majeſtie is pleaſed to declare by me, that no other oath ſhall be required of any miniſter at his entry, nor that which is ſet down in the act of parliament. And that it may appear how carefull his Majeſtie is that no corruption nor innovation ſhall creep into this church, neither yet any ſcandall, vice, or fault of any perſon whatſoever, cenſurable or puniſhable by the aſſembly, go along unpuniſhed, his Majeſtie is content to declare by me, and aſſure all his good people, that generall aſſemblies ſhall be kept ſo oft, and als oft as the affairs of this church ſhall require. And that none of his good ſubjects may have cauſe of grievances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the proceedings of the prelates, his Majeſtie is content that all and every one of the preſent biſhops, and their ſucceſſors, ſhall be anſwerable, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17424:6"/>from time to time cenſurable, according to their merits by the generall aſſembly. And to give all his Majeſties good people full aſſurance, that he never intended to admit any alteration or change in the true religion profeſt within this kingdome, and that they may be truely and fully ſatisfied of the reality of his intentions and integrity of the ſame, his Majeſtie hath been pleaſed to require and command all his good ſubjects to ſubſcribe the confeſſion of faith, and band for maintenance thereof, and of his Majeſties perſon and authority, formerly ſigned by his dear father, <hi>in anno</hi> 1580. and now alſo requireth all theſe of this preſent aſſembly to ſubſcribe the ſame. And it is his Majeſties will, that this be inſert and regiſtrate in the books of aſſembly, as a teſtimonie to poſteritie, not only of the ſinceritie of his intentions to the ſaid true religion, but alſo of his reſolutions to maintain and defend the ſame, and his ſubjects in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof.</p>
            <p>Which declaration was by our ſpeciall command and direction given in, and ſubſcribed by our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, upon proteſtation made by him that his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the regiſtration hereof, ſhould be no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the lawfulneſſe of this aſſembly; nor of any of the acts or deeds done, or to be done therein. And finding them in like ſort no waies to be ſatisfied therewith, and that nothing elſe was able to give them contentment, except at their own pleaſure they were permitted to overthrow all epiſcopall government in the church, and thereby to abrogate our publike lawes, ſtanding in vigour by the ſpace of many years
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17424:7"/>by-gone, and to alter the fundamental government of this kingdome, in taking away one of the three e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, contrary to expreſſe acts of Parliament. And leſt the continuance of their meetings might have produced other the like dangerous acts ſo deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie to royall authoritie, we were forced for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veening thereof, and for the reaſons and cauſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-mentioned, and divers others importing true monarchicall government, to diſſolve and break up the ſaid pretended aſſembly, and to diſcharge them of all farther meeting, treating, and concluding any thing therein: And yet in that calme and peaceable way, as our Commiſſioner before his removing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired their pretended moderator for that time to have ſaid prayer, and ſo concluded that daies ſeſſion, that ſo they might have had time to think upon the juſt reaſons of his refuſing to aſſiſt, or be any longer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the ſaid pretended aſſembly, and of the cauſes moving us to the diſſolving thereof: and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his earneſt urging the ſame, and being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to return the next morning to hear their anſwer; in place of all other ſatisfaction to his ſo reaſonable and moderate deſires, it was refuſed and met with a proteſtation of an high and extraordinary ſtraine, thereby preſuming to cite and call our Councell in queſtion, for their dutifull aſſiſtance and obedience to us and our Commiſſioner. And finding their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience thus to increaſe, we were conſtrained to diſcharge them of new again the next day thereafter by publike proclamation, under the pain of treaſon. And albeit that their contumacie is ſuch as hath not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17424:7"/>been heard of in former times, yet they ſhall never move us to alter the leaſt point or article of that we have already declared by proclamation, or declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under our Commiſſioners hand: All which was publickly read, and by our Commiſsioner required to be inſert and regiſtrate in the books of aſſembly, therein to remain as a teſtimonie to poſteritie, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the ſinceritie of our intentions to the true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo of our reſolution to maintain and defend the ſame, and our ſubjects in the profeſsion thereof: And perceiving likewaies that in contempt of our proclamation at Glaſgow the 29. of November, they goe ſtill on to conveen, meet, and to make illegall and unwarrantable acts, we have conceived it fitting to forewarn all our good ſubjects of the danger that they may incurre by being inſnared by theſe their unlawfull procedures. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe do not only liberate and free them from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to any of the pretended acts, made, or to be made at the ſaid pretended aſſembly, or comittees direct therefrom, but alſo do free them from all pain and cenſure which the ſaid pretended aſſembly ſhall inflict upon them, or any of them. And therefore do diſcharge and prohibit all our ſubjects, that they nor none of them acknowledge nor give obedience to any pretended acts nor conſtitutions made or to be made at the ſaid pretended meetings, under all higheſt pains. And we command, charge, and inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite all presbyteries, ſeſsions of kirks, miniſters within this realme, that none of them preſume nor take upon hand privately nor publikely in their ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17424:8"/>and meetings, nor in their conferences, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, nor no other manner of way, to authoriſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, juſtifie, or allow the ſaid unlawfull meeting, or aſſembly at Glaſgow: neither yet to make any act thereupon, nor to do any other thing private or publike, which may ſeem to countenance the ſaid unlawfull aſſembly, under the pain to be repute, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and eſteemed and purſued as guilty of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull meeting, and to be puniſhed therefore with all rigour: And ſiclike we command all and ſundry Noblemen, Barons, Gentlemen, Magiſtrates, and all other our lieges who ſhall happen to be preſent and hear any miniſters either in publick or private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and ſpeeches, or in their ſermons, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and allow the ſaid unlawfull aſſembly, rail and utter any ſpeeches againſt our royal commandments or proceedings of us, or our Councell, for puniſhing or ſuppreſsing ſuch enormities, that they make rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and report thereof to our Councell, and furniſh probation, to the effect the ſame may be accordingly puniſhed, as they will anſwer to us thereupon: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying them who ſhall hear and conceal the ſaid ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that they ſhall be eſteemed as allowers of the ſame, and ſhall accordingly be taken order with, and puniſhed therefore without favour. And to this effect we likewaies ſtraitly charge and command all Judges whatſoever within this realme, Clerks and Writers, not to grant or paſſe any bill, ſummons, or letters, ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other execution whatſoever, upon any act or deed proceeding from the ſaid pretended aſſembly, and all keepers of the ſignet from ſignetting thereof, and that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17424:8"/>under all higheſt pains. And becauſe we gave order and warrant to our Commiſſioner to make open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, not only of our ſenſe, but even of the true meaning of the confeſſion of faith, <hi>in anno</hi> 1580. by which it may clearly appear, that as we never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby to exclude epiſcopacie, ſo by no right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction can it be other wayes interpreted, as is more nor evident by the reaſons contained in the ſaid decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and many more, which for brevity (the thing in it ſelf being ſo clear) are omitted. Herefore we do not only prohibit and diſcharge all our ſubjects from ſubſcribing any band, or giving any writ, ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or oath to, or upon any act, or deed that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the foreſaid pretended aſſembly, but alſo do require them not to ſubſcribe, nor ſwear the ſaid confeſſion in no other ſenſe then that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſaid declaration, and manifeſtly emitted by our Commiſsioner, under all higheſt paines. And that none of our good ſubjects, who in their duty and bound obedience to us, ſhall refuſe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſaid pretended aſſembly, or any of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended acts, conſtitutions, warrants, or directions proceeding therefrom, may have juſt ground of fear of danger or harm by doing thereof, we do by theſe promiſe, and upon the word of a King oblige our ſelves by all the royall authoritie and power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath endowed us, to protect and defend them, and every one of them in their perſons, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and goods, againſt all and whatſoever perſon or perſons who ſhal dare or preſume to call in queſtion, trouble, or any waies moleſt them, or any of them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17424:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore. And our will is, and we charge you ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and command, that incontinent theſe our letters ſeen, you paſſe, and make publication hereof by open proclamation at the market croſſe of Edinburgh, and other places needfull, wherethrough none pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ignorance of the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given from our Court at Whitehall <date>the eighth day of December, and of our Reigne the fourteenth year, 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Per Regem.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17424:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
